A Guide to the Papers of the Tyler and Related Families 1765-1986
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Tyler and Related Families 1765-1986
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11250, -a, -b, -c
ca. 1,350 items (7 Hollinger boxes, ca. 3 linear shelf feet)
This collection consists of the family papers of the Tyler and related families of Amherst and Bedford Counties, Virginia, ca. [1765]-1986, including correspondence; diary of Mrs. M.L. Wood; financial and legal documents, including accounts, receipts, wills, copies and originals of deeds, and land plats; Amherst County Poll Books and papers related to the local government of Amherst County; genealogy; invitations; memoranda books; news clippings; poetry and other writings; specifications, drawings, and price lists for engines, tools, and other industrial machinery; notebooks; University of Virginia Chemistry Diplomas (transferred to the University Archives Diploma File); and bound volumes. Other families in the collection include: the Cumbie Family, the Holt Family, the Martin Family, the Miller Family, the Wilson Family, Wingfield Family, and the Wood Family.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accessions #11,250, -a were given by Elizabeth Tyler Chambers, Marion Tyler Huber, and Dorothy Tyler Obrochta through Tyron E. Huber, Jr., Sterling, Virginia, on July 8, 1996, and September 9, 1996; #11, 250- b was given to the Library by Mary Miller Woods, Charlottesville, Virginia, on October 2, 1996; and #11,250-c was given by Elizabeth Tyler Chambers, Marion Tyler Huber, and Dorothy Tyler Obrochta through Tyron E. Huber, Jr., Sterling, Virginia, on October 31, 1996.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence involving the Cumbie Family of Rustburg, Campbell County, Virginia. This correspondence includes: Willie A. Daniel, Company K, 58th Infantry, A.E.F., Germany, to Fannie (Mrs. Luther C.) Cumbie (d. 1940), February 24, 1919, concerning the death of Volney Cumbie, and transcripts of the World War I letters of Volney Eugene Cumbie (1887-191[8]) to his family.
Letters addressed to Mary Miller Woods (Mrs, Steven Philip) Holt These letters include the following correspondents: chiefly Lucile Francke, Minersville, Utah, but also a few letters from Mrs. F.B. Robinson and Mrs. L.M. Robinson and are concerned mostly with family and personal news.
Letters to and from Martin Family members These letters include the following correspondents and subjects: Martha Shaw, Oak Grove, Pike, Missouri, urging her brother, Howard Martin, to settle in Missouri (1844 May 31); Mattie Martin (1861 Oct 13); William & James Martin, Bowling Green, Kentucky, Colonel Wharton, 51st Regiment, Floyd's Brigade re Civil War (1862 Jan 24); John Goode, Jr. re the possible exemption of service for Mr. Wingfield (1862 Apr 19); J.D. Martin, Camp Sahara, Dinwiddie County, Virginia, mentioning Ulysses S. Grant and Petersburg (18[64?] Jul 10); Elizabeth G. Dawson re war prices and the breastworks on the hills of Amherst County, visible from her windows (186[?] Jul 10); and George H. Dameron re the estate of Howard Martin (1870 Nov 7).
Letters to and from Martin Family members These letters include the following correspondents and subjects: Martha Shaw, Oak Grove, Pike, Missouri, urging her brother, Howard Martin, to settle in Missouri (1844 May 31); Mattie Martin (1861 Oct 13); William & James Martin, Bowling Green, Kentucky, Colonel Wharton, 51st Regiment, Floyd's Brigade re Civil War (1862 Jan 24); John Goode, Jr. re the possible exemption of service for Mr. Wingfield (1862 Apr 19); J.D. Martin, Camp Sahara, Dinwiddie County, Virginia, mentioning Ulysses S. Grant and Petersburg (18[64?] Jul 10); Elizabeth G. Dawson re war prices and the breastworks on the hills of Amherst County, visible from her windows (186[?] Jul 10); and George H. Dameron re the estate of Howard Martin (1870 Nov 7).
Letters to Joseph Miller These letters include several from Henry Booth (via John Farey) and John Farey about a report on the merits of various types of locomotive engine boilers (1832-1833) and letters from various British foundries and manufacturers with price lists for heavy engineer tools and other industrial machinery (1857). For related material see the folder "Specifications, Drawings, and Price Lists for Engines, Tools, and Other Machinery" in Box 7.
Letters to Bessie Tyler These letters to Bessie Tyler, Lynchburg, Virginia, are chiefly concerned with personal and family news, religious meetings, and social engagements. Correspondents and subjects include: Mattie J. Emett, Nelson County, Virginia; Lucie [M. Wingfield (1857-1898)?]; Fannie Blackburn, Clinton County, Ohio, re a description of the Cincinnati Exposition (1874 Oct 12); Sarah V. Brook; Mattie E. Jones; Charles [Tyler?]; Bettie Tyler; Mary Dameron; Burra O. Bell; and the death of Sarah Ann Elizabeth Tyler, 1836-1878 (1878 Nov 25).
Letters to Bessie Tyler These letters to Bessie Tyler, Lynchburg, Virginia, are chiefly concerned with personal and family news, religious meetings, and social engagements. Correspondents and subjects include: Mattie J. Emett, Nelson County, Virginia; Lucie [M. Wingfield (1857-1898)?]; Fannie Blackburn, Clinton County, Ohio, re a description of the Cincinnati Exposition (1874 Oct 12); Sarah V. Brook; Mattie E. Jones; Charles [Tyler?]; Bettie Tyler; Mary Dameron; Burra O. Bell; and the death of Sarah Ann Elizabeth Tyler, 1836-1878 (1878 Nov 25).
Letters to Fannie (Frances Fielden)Tyler (1881-1959) from Janet Amonette Ferrell These letters from her former teaching associate, Janet Ferrell, discuss her delight in her newlywed status (1915 Jun 13 & Jul 14); the birth of a child (1917 Feb 23); and her regret at the death of Fannie's father, F.B. Tyler (1921 Sep 1).
Letters to Fannie Tyler from Miscellaneous Correspondents Correspondents include: Kate A. Davis; Royall Holt (Mrs. John Lewis) Tyler (chiefly letters written to Fannie while she was visiting other relatives in Ft. Bragg, North Carolina (1923-1925); Mary Dameron Dise [1869-1961?]; Myrtis & Walter Anderson; Thelma Carey; Samuel L. [Drewville ?] re the death of his sister-in-law (1928 Jul 14); and Edwin Tyler.
Letters to F.B. (Fielden Bonepart) Tyler (1842-1921) F.B. Tyler was a member of the Local Board of Review of Assessments, Chairman of the Amherst County Board of Supervisors, President of the Board of County Commissioners, and Overseer of the Poor, Elon District, for Amherst County, and much of the material concerning Tyler is related to his role in the local government of Amherst County. Correspondents and subjects include: Bettie Tyler; T.H. Campbell; N. Fairfax; M.H. Garland; Anne Ridgway; J.H. Cash; John D. Wattles; A.C. Berryman; E.M. Ware; H.C. James; Charles L. Ellis; Jesse Sowers; H.A. Strode; M.F. Layne; C.L. Williams; E.B. McGinnis; B.A. Davis & J.W. Giles; James M. Watts; H.W. Stevens; Clarence J. Campbell; S.F. Cox; A.W. Mosby; William Watts; Mrs. J.K. Walker; Samuel W. Williams; J.M. Morris; S.R. Church; Helen C. Joyner; W.H. Carter; R.H. Drummond; Elizabeth Tyler Easley; Rep. H.D. Flood re tobacco growing (1913 Feb 25); road conditions in Amherst County and the re-election of F.B. Tyler (1899 Mar 25); the visit of President and Mrs. McKinley and Theodore Roosevelt to Roanoke, Virginia (1901 Apr 30).
Letters to Kate Tyler Correspondents and subjects include: Mattie Tyler; Helen B. Joyner; Bettie Tyler; R.B. Wortham; James E. Tyler; Jennie B. Tyler; J.C. Tyler; Emma Dameron; cousin Rebecca; J. Tyler; John Tyler; Sarah V. Brook; F.E. Wren; L.A. Sully; E.M. Ware; F.F. Tyler; Lizzie B. Williams; Lucy [Lowry?]; Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Holt Tyler; B. Johnathan; J.D. Tyler; MW Hunt; a description of a trip out West to Missouri, Nebraska, Kansas, through the Indian Territory by train to Texas (1880 Feb 28); the death of Bessie Tyler (1914 Jan 5); and a letter from a student attending a summer class on geography at the University of Virginia (1908 Jul 22). A separate folder contains letters from doctors and druggists to Kate Tyler concerning her illness.
Letters to Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Holt Tyler (1892-1971) from Rufus & Rosa Holt These letters to Royall Tyler, at Pedlar Mills, Virginia, are from her brother and sister-in-law Rufus (1895- ?) and Rosa Holt (1902- ?), who were living in McGill, Nevada, where he worked for the copper mines. Katherine Royall Holt was the daughter of Taylor Holt and Francis H. Kyle (1867-1959) and was born in Leadville, Colorado, and married in Buena Vista, Colorado, in 1916, to John Lewis Tyler, Jr. (1886-1942). At the time of these letters, Royall Tyler was living in Lynchburg and was helping to care for her mother. Subjects in the letters include: the copper mill and its hectic production schedule (1950 Oct 11); observations and reservations about the atomic bomb testing (1951 Feb 7 & 11); adventures at a well child clinic (1951 Feb 18); a description of a dust storm (1951 Mar 27); and a reaction to the invention of television (1952 Apr 15).
Letters to Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Holt Tyler (1892-1971) from Steven Philip Holt Steven Philip Holt (1893-1978), married to Mary Miller Woods and employed by the U.S. Bureau of Mines, writes to his sister Royall chiefly concerning the care and finances of their mother at Pedlar Mills.
Letters to Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Holt Tyler (1892-1971) from Taylor Holt, Jr. Subjects in the letters from Taylor Holt, Jr. to his sister include: the visit of General Douglas MacArthur to Park Forest, Illinois (1950 Apr 26); reports on the progress of her son, Edwin Tyler (1927- ), who left teaching in Virginia to look for work in Chicago (1951 Jun 13, Jul 13, Dec 17); the wedding of his daughter Jane (1951 Aug-Sep); and the care and finances of their mother is mentioned throughout.
Letters to Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Holt Tyler (1892-1971) from Helen Leavens Helen (Mrs. C.F.) Leavens, apparently a niece of Royall Tyler's, writes from Alexandria, Virginia, about family and personal news. Other topics include: a description of the Eisenhower Inaugural Parade (1953 Jan 21).
Letters to Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Holt Tyler (1892-1971) from Jean and Paul Petersen These letters appear to be from another niece and her husband, living in Washington, D.C., and are chiefly concerned with family and personal news.
Letters to Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Holt Tyler (1892-1971) from Edwin H. Tyler These letters are from Royall Tyler's youngest son, Edwin (1927- ?), who has moved from Virginia, to find work in Chicago, near his uncle Taylor Holt, Jr. Most of the letters are concerned with his job search, family and personal news, his work with the Coca-Cola Company as a sales promotion agent, and his engagement and marriage to Barbara June Shaw.
Letters to Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Holt Tyler (1892-1971) from Eielden B. Tyler These letters are from one of Royall Tyler's sons, Fielden Bradford Tyler ["Flip"] (1925-1989), who married Elizabeth Cocroft ["Betsy"] and was living in Washington, D.C. where he attended school. They contain much family and personal news and discuss his work as a draftsman at the U.S. Bureau of Standards.
Letters to Sallie Tyler Subjects in the letters to Sarah Ann Elisabeth Tyler (1836-1878) at Harris Creek, Amherst County, include: Thomas P. Wise and his church work during the Civil War period (1863 Dec 20; 1864 Apr 17); the illness of Robert [Labat?](1864 Oct 27); a description of a trip to the Eastern Shore (1868 Jul 28); financial appeals from Pastor John N. Jones concerning the building of a Methodist Church at Gordonsville (1870 Mar 1); the death of John Lewis Tyler, Sr. [1808-1872] (1872 Feb 27); and ice in the Baltimore Harbor (1877 Jan 24). Additional correspondents include: Sallie Bowles, a frequent correspondent and friend from Baltimore, Maryland; [Martha?] L. Wheeler; H.P. Crute; John P. Mann; Pastor [J.?]W. Howard; Mary W. Teasley; Emma Wortham; Rebecca Voorheis; John W. Howard; R.M. Cox; Emma J. Staples; V.L. Pettyjohn; Bettie Tyler; N. Thomas; J.D. Blackwell; Annie E. Fairfax; and E.H.H. Winslow.
Letters to and from Mary Ann (Miller) Woods Subjects include family and social news. Correspondents include: Mary Ann Miller to her cousin, James Todhunter, Carlisle, England; R.W. Wood, Charlottesville, Virginia; Ann C. Bankhead; Eleanor Monroe Bankhead; and Elizabeth B. Lewis.
Letters to and from Miscellaneous Correspondents Correspondents include: Kate Tyler; Horace Wilson; R. Walker Wilson; William H. Elliott, Engineer's Office, Richmond, C.S.A.; Annie E. Roberts; J.W. Harris; [Mary?] Camilla [Tyler?]; M.F. Layne; Bella Fairfax; and Sallie Tyler.
Legal & Financial Papers These papers include copies of the wills of John P. Wilson (1862 Oct 1) and James McGee (1867 Mar 30); a tax receipt to Howard Martin for "1 Negro" (1821); and a "Negro" hire for James D. Martin (1860), who was a private in Company G, 2nd Virginia Cavalry. Among the legal and financial papers of William H. Tyler are receipts for his services as a teacher in Amherst County, Virginia, ca. 1856-1858, tax receipts for slaves (1859) and papers pertaining to his parole and loyalty oath to the United States of America (1865). Also present in the collection are memoranda books belonging to F.B. Tyler, J.G. Williams, and William H. Tyler. Other miscellaneous items in the collection can be found in the folder listing.
Organization
The collection is arranged in two series: I) Correspondence (Boxes 1-4) and II) Legal, Financial, & Miscellaneous Papers (Boxes 4-7, Oversize folder, & 2M Ledger).
Contents List
- CORRESPONDENCE (Box 1-4)
  - Letters to Fannie (Mrs. Luther C.) Cumbie 1919-1939 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Volney Eugene Cumbie (1887-191[8])- Transcripts in a Notebook [1917-1918] (Box 1)
  - Letters to Mrs. Steven Philip Holt 1929-1932, n.d., 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters to and from Martin Family members 1844-1870, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Letters to Joseph Miller 1832-1857 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Bessie Tyler 1869-1912,n.d., 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters to Fannie Tyler from Janet Amonette Ferrell 1915-1922, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters to Fannie Tyler from Miscellaneous Correspondents 1915-1951 (Box 2)
  - Letters to F.B. Tyler 1871-1921, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters to Kate Tyler 1862-1914, n.d., 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters to Kate Tyler, chiefly from doctors and drugists 1880-1884, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Letters to Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Tyler from Rufus & Rosa Holt 1950-1953, n.d., 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Letters to Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Tyler from Steven Philip Holt 1951-1953 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Tyler from Taylor Holt, Jr. 1950-1953 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Tyler from Helen Leavens 1949-1953 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Tyler from Miscellaneous correspondents 1951-1956 (Box 3)
  - Letters to royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Tyler from Jean & Paul Petersen 1950-1953 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Royall (Mrs. John Lewis) Tyler from Edwin H. Tyler 1951-1953, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Letters to Royall (Mrs.Joh Lewis) Tyler from Fielden B. Tyler 1950-1953 (Box 4)
  - Letters to Sallie Tyler 1860-1878, n.d., 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Letters to Mary Ann (Miller) Wood 1822-1828 (Box 4)
  - Letters to and from Miscellaneous Correspondents 1851-1977 (Box 4)
- Legal, Financial, & Miscellaneous Papers (Box 4-7)
  - Amherst County, Virginia - Papers 1882-1901, 1928, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Amherst County, Virginia - Poll Books 1902-1903 (Box 4)
  - Diary of Mrs. M.L. Wood ca. 1928-1930 (Box 5)
  - Genealogical Notes re the Martin Family, Tyler Family and the Wilson Family n.d. (Box 5)
  - Genealogy - Computer Printouts n.d., 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Invitations ca. 1860-1950 (Box 5)
  - Legal & Financial Papers [1765]-1937, 1959-1986, n.d., 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Legal & financial Papers of the Cumbie Family, Rustburg, Virginia 1893-1940 (Box 5)
  - Legal & financial Papers of Martha Jane Martin (1833-1916), William Webb Martin ([1818]-1903), and James Dabney Martin (1823-1864) 1816-1917 (Box 6)
  - Legal & Financial Papers of Fielden B. Tyler (1842-1921) 1882-1917 (Box 6)
  - Legal & Financial Papers of William H. Tyler (1834-1910) 1856-1906 (Box 6)
  - Legal & Financial Papers of Charles Wingfield 1769-1819 (Box 6)
  - Memoranda Books 1883-1895, n.d., 7 volumes (Box 6)
  - Memoranda Books belonging to Williams H. Tyler 1861-1862, 1865-1862, 5 volumes (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Papers 1895-1972 (Box 7)
- News clippings 1878-1971, n.d. (Box 7)
- Poetry and Other Writings 1878-1971, n.d. (Box 7)
- Receipt Book for F.B. Tyler, Overseer Roads, Elon District, Amherst County, Virginia ca. 1899-1902 (Box 7)
- Roll Book for Farmer's Alliance No. 501, kept by F.B. Tyler 1890 (Box 7)
- School Notebooks n.d. (Box 7)
- Specifications, Drawings & Price Lists for Engines, Tools & Other Machinery 1832-1857, n.d. (Box 7)
- Map Showing route of Proposed Road from Tinsley's Cedar Gate on Bethel Road Via 'Monroe' to Old Stage Road" [Amherst County, Virginia?] 1877 (Oversize 14)
- Indenture between William D. Dowe & wife and Elizabeth Graham Ashmead 1872 Nov 23 (Oversize M-21)
- Plat of Lands of J.F. Fredericksen, Amherst County, Virginia 1891 (Box M-21)
- Certificates of Distinction bestowed by the Staunton Public Schools upon Malcolm A. Holliday 1901, 1903 (Oversize M-21)
- 3 University of Virginia Diplomas for Chemistry issued to Malcolm A. Holliday 1911, 1914, removed and placed in the UVA Archives Diploma file (Oversize M-21)
- Plat of the subdivision of "Tyler Tract" 1914, 3 Copies (Oversize M-21)
- Plat of Subdivision of the Estate of F.B. & Mary C. Tyler, Elon District, Amherst County, Virginia 1922 Sep, 5 Copies (Oversize M-21)
- Membership Certificate from the United Daughters of the Confederacy to Fannie F. Tyler, daughter of Fielding B. Tyler, Company D., 20th Battalion, Virginia Heavy Artillery 1925 Aug 8, Damaged and Fragile (Oversize M-21)
- 2 Drawings of Machinery n.d. (Oversize M-21)
- Price List of Self-Acting Machine Tools, by Smith, Beacock, & Tannett, Victoria Foundry, Leeds, England n.d. (Oversize M-21)
- "Descendants of Charles Tyler Family Genealogical Chart" n.d., computer generated (Box M-21)
- Journal of W. H. Tyler & Company, Lynchburg, Virginia (1888-1903) and "House Book" kept by [royall] Mrs. John Tyler (ca. 1961) all in one volume 1888-1903 & ca. 1961